Baruj Salinas
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Baruj Salinas papers
1971-1996
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Salinas, Baruj
0.4 linear feet
The Baruj Salinas papers measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1971-1996. The collection documents the artist's prolific painting career and his friendships and professional relationships with a variety of contemporary artist in the U.S. and Europe. The papers of Baruj Salinas are an important addition to the documentation of Cuban-American art and artists.
Biographical Note
Born in Havana, painter Baruj Salinas' (b. 1938) career began in the field of architecture. He graduated from the University of Ohio with an architectural degree and left Cuba permanently in 1959. Salinas settled in Miami and later moved to Barcelona where he studied alongside artists Joan Miró and Antoni Tàpies.
Scope and Content Note
The Baruj Salinas papers measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1971-1996. The collection primarily consists of letters from friends and artists. Also found are diary entries, scattered financial and business papers, printed material, and photographs. Of special interest in the last series are photographs taken of a visit to the home and art studio of Spanish artist Joan Miró.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Diary Entries, 1982 (box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Letters Received, 1979-1996, undated (box 1; 21 folders)
Series 3: Financial Papers, 1993-1994 (box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1976-1992, undated (box 1; 2 folders)
Series 5: Photographs, 1971-1992, undated (box 1; 3 folders)
Series 6: Miscellany, 1992 (box 1; 1 folder)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976 -- Photographs; Cubiles, Miguel -- Photographs; Cuevas, José Luis, 1934- -- Photographs; Fonts, Marilyn -- Photographs; Franqui, Carlos, 1921- -- Photographs; Gutierrez, Osvaldo -- Photographs; Lozano Castro, Alfredo -- Photographs; Miró, Joan, 1893- -- Photographs; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899- -- Photographs; Vidal, Juan -- Photographs; Stedlijk Museum (Amsterdam, Holland); Rijksmuseum (Netherlands); Van Gogh Museum, Amsterdam
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- Florida -- Miami; Painters -- Cuba -- Havana; Hispanic American artists; Cuban American art
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
Alejandro, Ramon; Algaze, Mario Arturo, 1947-; Armand, Octavio, 1946-; Carulla, Ramón, 1938-; Cubiles, Miguel; Estopiñán, Roberto, 1921-; Ferrer, Joaquin; Fonts, Marilyn; Franqui, Camilo; Franqui, Carlos, 1921-; Godoy, Gustavo G.; Kohler, Elizabeth; Kohler, Peter; Linder, Gisele; Lozano Castro, Alfredo; Macia, Carlos A., 1951-1994; McBride, Robert H.; Pau-Llosa, Ricardo; Riverón, Enrique; Roel, Guillermo; Rodríguez, Bélgica, 1941-; Samelson, Henry; Salinas, Rosa; Salinas, Isaac; Serur, David; Soriano, Rafael, 1920-; Toonkel, Gail; Valente, José Angel; Ward, Bettie
Provenance
Baruj Salinas donated his papers to the Archives of American Art in 1997.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Diary Entries, 1982, Series 1:; (box 1; 1 folder)
  Diary entries record five days of a vacation trip to Amsterdam taken to visit art museums including the Stedelijk Museum, the Van Gogh Museum, the Rijkmuseum, and others.
  - Loose daily entries, 1982 (Box 1 (hol))
- Letters Received, 1979-1996, undated, Series 2:; (box 1; 21 folders)
  Letters are addressed to Baruj Salinas and concern such topics as upcoming exhibitions, exhibition reviews, and other art related subjects in addition to personal matters. Correspondents are Ramón Alejandro, Mario Algaze, Octavio Armand, Ramón Carulla, Miguel Cubiles, Roberto Estopiñan, Joaquin Ferrer, Marilyn Fonts, Camilo Franqui, Carlos Franqui, Gustavo G. Godoy, Elisabeth and Peter Kohler, Gisèle Linder, Alfredo Lozano, Carlos Macía, Robert H. McBride, Ricardo Pau-Llosa, Enrique Riverón, Belgica Rodríguez, Guillermo Roel, Henry Samelson, David Serur, Jorge L. Sicre, Rafael Soriano, Gail Toonkel, Joëlle Tremblant, José Augel Valiente, Bettie Ward, members of the Salinas family and others. This series also contains greeting cards and postcards.
  - A File, 1979-1996, n.d (Box 1 (hol))
  - B File, 1979-1994 (Box 1 (hol))
  - C File, 1980-1996, n.d (Box 1 (hol))
  - D File, 1982, 1991-1993 (Box 1 (hol))
  - E File, 1980-1982, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - F File, 1980-1981, 1992-1993, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - G File, 1982-1983, 1991-1993 (Box 1 (hol))
  - H File, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (hol))
  - I File, 1980-1982, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - J File, 1996, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - K File, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (hol))
  - L File, 1980, 1990-1996 (Box 1 (hol))
  - M File, 1980-1996, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - N File, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (hol))
  - P-Q File, 1980, 1993, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - R File, 1979-1993, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - S File, 1979-1992, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - T File, 1982-1993, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - V-Z File, 1980-1992, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - Letters from family members, 1979-1993, undated (Box 1 (hol))
  - Greeting cards and postcards, 1980-1996, undated (Box 1 (hol))
- Financial Papers, 1993-1994, Series 3:; (box 1; 1 folder)
  Financial papers include hotel receipts, copies of cancelled checks and other financial material. Printed Material, 1981-1992, consists of newspaper and magazine clippings and two published articles about Judaism by Julio Algazi Maya.
  - Bank deposits and receipts, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (hol))
- Printed Material, 1976-1992, undated, Series 4:; (box 1; 2 folders)
  - Exhibition invitations, 1976-1992 (Box 1 (hol))
  - Magazine and newspaper clippings, 1992, undated (Box 1 (hol))
- Photographs, 1971-1992, undated, Series 5:; (box 1; 3 folders)
  Found are color and black and white photographs of art work and of Salinas with artists Alexander Calder, Miguel Cubiles, Rufino Tamayo, Joan Miró, Osvaldo Gutierrez, Alfredo Lozano, Juan Vidal, José Luis Cuevas, and others. Also found are black and white photographs of paintings by Salinas.
  - Photographs, 1971-1992, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1 (hol))
- Miscellany, 1992, Series 6:; (box 1; 1 folder)
  - Handwritten poem, "An Island", 1992 (Box 1 (hol))